hey what's up guys my name is Aero and
welcome back to my C++ series So today
we're going to learn all about how the
C++ compiler works so let's take a step
back and think about this for a minute
what is the big picture here what is a
C++ compiler actually responsible for so
we write our C++ code AS text it that's
all it is it's just a text file and then
we need some way to transform that text
into an actual application that our
computer can run in going from that text
form to an actual executable binary we
basically have two main operations that
need to happen one of them is called
compiling and one of them is called
linking in this video we're just going
to talk about compiling I've actually
made another video specifically covering
linking so you might want to check that
out as well the link will be in the
description below so with that being
said the only thing that the C++
compiler actually needs to do is to take
our text files and convert them into an
intermediate format called an object
file those object files can then be
passed on to the Linker and the Linker
could do all of its linky things but
anyway we're talking about compiling
here the compiler actually does several
things when it produces these object
files firstly it needs to pre-process
our code which means that any
pre-processor statements get evaluated
then and there once our code has been
pre-processed we move on to more or less
tokenizing and paing and basically
sorting out this English C++ language
into a format that the compiler can
actually understand and reason with this
basically results in something called an
abstract syntax tree being created which
is basically a representation of our
code but as an abstract syntax tree the
the compiler's job at the end of the day
is to convert all of our code into
either constant data or instructions
once the compiler has created this
abstract syntax tree it can begin
actually generating code now this code
is going to be the actual machine code
that our CPU will execute we also wind
up with various other data such as a
place to store all of our constant
variables and that's essentially all the
compiler does it's not crazy complicated
it of course does get very complicated
as your actual code complexity grows but
that is the gist of it that's all that
it does we're going to go ahead and jump
into this and take a look at what each
stage actually does so that you guys can
see how it all works so let's go okay so
here we've got a simple Holo World
application you might remember this from
the house C++ Works video that I
recently made we basically just got this
main function which calls log which is
actually defined inside this log. CPP
file and it simply just prints our
message to the screen and we wind up
with a simple application which says
hello world if we pop over into our
output directory debug here you can see
that it's generated a hell world.exe
file and then back in the project
directory in debug it's generated a
main. obj and log. obj file so what the
compiler has done is has generated
object files for each of our C++ files
for each of our translation units now
every CPP file that our project contains
that we actually tell the compiler hey
compile this CPP file every single one
of those files will result in an object
file these CPP files are things called
translation units essentially you have
to realize that c C++ doesn't care about
files files are not something that
exists in C++ for example in Java your
class name has to be tied to your file
name and your folder hierarchy has to be
tied to your package and there's all of
this going on because Java expects
certain FS to exist in C++ that is not
the case there is no such thing as a
file a file is just a way to feed the
compiler with source code you're
responsible for telling the compiler
what kind of file type this is and how
the compiler should treat that now of
course if you create a file with the
extension CPP the compiler is going to
treat that as a C++ file similarly if I
make a file with the extension C orh the
compil is going to treat the C file like
a C file and not a C++ file and it's
going to treat theh file like a header
file these are basically just default
conventions that are in place you can
override any of them and that's just how
the compiler will will deal with it if
you don't tell it how to deal with it I
could go around making Cherno files and
telling the compiler to compile that and
that would be totally fine as long as I
tell the compiler hey this file is a C++
file please compile it like a C++ file
so just remember files have no meaning
okay remember that it's important so
that being said every C++ file that we
feed into the compiler and we tell it
this is a C++ file please compile it it
will compile it as a translation unit
and a translation unit will result in an
object file it's actually quite common
to sometimes include CPP files in other
CPP files and create basically one big
CPP file with a lot of files in it if
you do something like that and then you
only compile the one CPP file you're
going to basically result in one
translation unit and thus one object
file so that's why there's that
terminology split between what a
translation unit is and what a CPP file
actually is because a CPP file doesn't
necessarily have to equal a translation
unit however if you just make a project
with individual CPP files and you never
include them in each other then yes
every CPP file will be a translation
unit and every CPP file will generate an
object file now these are actually
pretty big you can see this one's 30
kiloby and this one's 46 KOB the reason
for that is because we're including IO
stream and that has a lot of stuff in it
so that's why they're so big and because
of that they're actually pretty
complicated so before we dive in and
take a look at what's actually in the
files let's create something a little
bit more simple I'm going to right click
on source file hit add new item this is
going to be a C++ file I'm going to call
it math. CPP and hit add over here I'm
just going to write a very basic
multiply function which multiplies two
numbers together I'm not going to
include any files in here or anything
I'm just going to write a very simple
function it's going to return an integer
it's going to be called multiply it's
going to take two parameters int a and
int
B it's then going to create a result
variable which stores the result of a *
B and then we're going to return that
result variable nice and simple that's
it let's hit control 7 to build that
file you can see over here that it's
built it successfully I'm actually going
to just resize Visual Studio a little
bit just to make it easier so now you
can see the output window a bit better
if we look back into our output
directory you can see that we've got
this math. obj file now and it's 4
kilobytes before we take a look at what
exactly is in that object file let's
talk about the first edge of compilation
which I mentioned earlier pre-processing
during the pre-processing stage the
compiler will basically just go through
all of our pre-processing statements and
evaluate them the ones that we commonly
use are include Define if and if def
there are also pragma statements which
tell the compiler exactly what to do but
we'll talk about them in another video
so let's take a look at one of the most
common pre-processor statements that we
have hash include how does that work so
hash include is actually really simple
you basically specify which file you
want to include and then the
pre-processor will open that file read
all of its contents and just paste it
into the file where you wrote your
include statement and that's it it's
really really simple and I'm about to
prove that so back over here I'm just
going to make a header file I'm going to
right click on header files hit add new
item this is going to be a header file
and I'm going to call it end brace and
then click add okay we're going to wipe
out whatever was in this file and I'm
just going to type in a closing curve
brace that is it that's our entire file
so now back in math Topp you can see
that we've reasonably written a closing
curly bracket here for our multiply
function let's go ahead and wipe that
out if we compile our file Now by
hitting contrl F7 you can see that the
compiler complains about the left brace
being unmatched at the end of the file
so instead of fixing this like a normal
person and just adding in our ending
brace let's go ahead and include our end
brace header file so I'll type in hash
include and
Brace and there we go let's hit contrl
F7 to compile that and look it compiled
successfully of course it did because
all the compiler did was open this end
brace file copy whatever was in here and
then just paste it into here and that is
it okay header files solved you should
now know exactly how they work and how
you can use them there's actually a way
we can tell the compiler to Output a
file which contains the result of all of
these pre-processor evaluations that
have happened if we bring back our
include end brace and then right click
on our hello world project and hit
properties under cc++ and then
pre-processor I'm going to set the
pre-process to a file to yes make sure
that you're editing your current
configuration and platform so that these
settings actually apply let's hit okay
and then we're going to just hit contrl
F7 to build this again if we bring up
our output directory you'll see this new
I file which is our pre-processed cc++
code let's open this in a text editor so
that we can look at it okay so here you
can see what the pre-processor has
actually generated you can see that our
source code had this include end brace
and yet the pre-processor code has just
inserted our end brace that was in that
H file that we've included pretty simple
stuff let's add some more pre-processor
statements and see what it does so back
in our file I'm going to restore our end
brace because I'm getting tired at
looking at that include I'm then going
to come up here and Define something I'm
going to define the word integer to be
int now don't ask me why I would ever do
this this is just an example the defined
pre-processor statement will B basically
just do a search for this word and
replace it with whatever follows so
let's replace our int here with the word
integer so that we actually return this
integer we can also do the same
here let's hit contrl F7 and if we look
back at our file you can see what's
happened it just looks normal int result
if we were to do something stupid here
like write the word Cho and then hit
contrl F7 if we go back to our file you
can see it now says Cho multiply and Cho
result pretty cool stuff let's play
around with this a little bit more let's
bring back our
int we'll get rid of this Define and
instead what I'm going to do is actually
just use something called if the if
pre-processor statement can let us
include or exclude code based on a given
condition so over here I'm just going to
write if one which in other words means
true and then just write an end if at
the end of this function I'll hit C
contrl F7 we'll go back to our
preprocessor file and you can see that
it looks exactly like it does here
without the if statement if I go back
here and I switch this off by writing
if0 Visual Studio will fade out our code
to show that it's disabled if I hit
contrl F7 and take a look at this file
we have no code so that's another great
example of a pre-processor statement all
right one more we'll look at include so
let's get rid of our if0 and then I'm
going to write include IO stream the
massive massive IO stream let's hit
control F7 let's look back at this and
whoo take a look at this we have in here
,62 3 lines and and there's our function
at the very bottom and then look this is
all that include IO stream has done now
of course IO stream also includes other
files so it's kind of like rolling a
snowball down a hill you can now
hopefully see why those object files
were so big because they included
iostream and that is a lot of code all
right great so that's the pre-processor
once that stage has done we can move on
to actually compiling our C++ code into
machine code if we go back to our
project here I'm going to get rid of
this include because we don't need it
and then I'm just going to hit contr F7
you should now see in our pre-process a
file that we're back to normal and in
fact I'm actually going to go into hello
world Hit properties and then disable
that pre-process to a file if you
actually read what pre-process to a file
does you'll see that it actually does
not produce an obj file so we need to
disable it so that we can actually build
our project let's hit okay and then
we'll hit contrl F7 to build our CPP
file you'll see that we should now get a
math. obj file which is actually up to
date so let's take a look at what's
actually inside our obj file if we open
this file with a text editor you'll see
that it's binary which doesn't really
help us too much but part of what is
actually inside here is the machine code
that our CPU will run when we call this
multiply function so because this is
just binary and completely unreadable
let's convert it into a form that might
actually be more readable by us there
are several ways we could do this but
I'm just going to use Visual Studio I'll
right click on Hollow world and hit
properties under cc++ and then output
files I'm going to set assembler output
to be set to assembly only listing and
then going to hit okay and we're going
to hit contrl F7 inside our output
directory you should see a math. Asm
file let's go ahead and open that with a
text editor okay so this is basically a
readable result of what that object file
actually contains if we go down over
here you'll see that we actually have
this function called multiply and then
we have a bunch of assembly instructions
these are the actual instructions that
our CPU will execute when we run the
function I'm not going to go into huge
detail about all of this assembly code
now I might save that for another video
but if we take a look over here you'll
see that our multiplication operation
actually happens here basically we load
the a variable into our eax register and
then we perform an IML instruction which
is a multiplication instruction on the B
variable and that a variable we're then
storing the result of that in a variable
called result and then moving it back
into eax to return it the reason this
kind of double move happens is because I
actually made a variable called result
and then returned it instead of just
returning a * B that's why we get this
moving eax into result and then moving
result into eax which is completely
redundant this is another a great
example of why if you set your compiler
not to optimize you're going to wind up
with slow code cuz it's doing extra
stuff like this for no reason if I go
back to my code and I actually get rid
of that result variable by just
returning a * B and then compile this
you'll see the assembly looks slightly
different because we're just doing imal
on B and eax and then that's it eax is
actually going to contain our return
value now all of this may look like a
lot of code and that's because we're
actually compiling in debug which
doesn't do any optimization and does
extra things to make sure that our Cod
is as verbose as possible and as easy to
debug as possible if we go back into our
project and right click here hit
properties I'm going to go over here
into optimization under the debug
configuration let's select maximize
speed if you try and compile this now
it'll actually give you an error because
you'll see that O2 and RTC is actually
incompatible so we'll have to go back
over here into code generation and make
sure that our basic runtime checks are
set to default which basically won't
perform runtime checks this is basically
just code that the compiler will insert
to help us with debugging let's hit
contrl F7 and look at that assembly file
again wow that looks a lot smaller we've
basically just got our variables being
loaded into a register and then the
multiplication and then that's it pretty
simple stuff you should now have a basic
idea of what the compiler actually does
when you tell it to optimize it
optimizes this is a pretty simple
example so let's take a look at
something a bit more advanced we'll take
a look at a slightly different example
in which case we don't actually take
anything in here but I decide to do
something like 5 time 2 we'll save that
file I'll go into my properties and make
sure that I disable optimization so
let's hit contr F7 and take a look at
our file you can see that what it's done
is actually really simple it's simply
moved 10 into our eax register which is
the register that will actually store
our return value in so if we take a look
at our code again it's basically just
simplified our 5 * 2 to be 10 because of
course there's no need to do something
like 5 * 2 two constant values at
runtime this is something called
constant folding where anything that is
constant that can be worked out at
compile time is let's make things more
interesting by involving another
function so for example I'm actually
going to write a log function which is
going to log a certain message of course
I don't actually want to make it log
anything because that would mean I would
have to include iostream which will
drastically complicate this so I'm just
going to get it to return that message
that it receives over here in multiply
I'm going to call log with the word
multiply I'm going to change this back
to be a and
B and we'll return a * B let's hit contr
F7 all right so let's take a look at
what our compiler has generated if we
scroll down a bit you'll see that we've
got this log function which doesn't
really do much but this actually will
just return our message you can see that
it's moving our message pointer into eax
which is our return register as we've
established so this is the log function
if we scroll up a little bit you'll see
the multiply function and then all we
have here is a call to log so right
before we actually do multiplication by
using the imal we actually call this log
function now you might be wondering why
this log function is decorated by what
seems like random characters and at
signs this is actually the function
signature this needs to uniquely Define
your function we'll talk more about this
in the linking video but essentially
when we have multiple objs and our
functions are defined in multiple objs
it's going to be the linker's job to
link all of them together and the way
that it's going to do that is it's going
to look up this function signature so
all you need to know here is that we're
calling this log function that's what
the compiler will actually do when you
call a function it will generate a call
instruction now in this case it might be
a little bit stupid because you can see
that we're simply calling log we're not
even storing the return value basically
this could be optimized quite a bit if
we go back here and we turn on
optimization to maximize speed and hit
contrl F7 you'll actually see that that
just disappears entirely yep the
compiler just decided that does nothing
I'm going to remove that code but you
should basically Now understand the gist
of how the compiler works it will take
our source files and output an object
file which contains machine code and any
other constant data that we've defined
that's basically it and now that we've
got these object files we can link them
into one executable which contains all
of the machine code that we actually
need to run and that's how we make a
program in C++ pretty simple make sure
that you check out my video on how the
link works so that you can see the next
step but apart from that hope you guys
enjoyed this video hope you learned
something new you should now have a
basic understanding of what the C++
compiler actually does and that's going
to be really important when it comes to
debugging and also when we get into more
advanced topics in the future make sure
you follow me on Twitter and Instagram
and if you really like this you can
support me on patreon I'll see you guys
next time goodbye
Voom